<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Marko Idzan</title>
	<atom:link href="/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description>Personal portfolio and blog</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Wed, 22 Dec 2021 21:12:28 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=5.8.2</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Upgrading from Windows 10 to Windows 11 on unsupported hardware</title>
		<link>/upgrading-from-windows-10-to-windows-11-on-unsupported-hardware/</link>
					<comments>/upgrading-from-windows-10-to-windows-11-on-unsupported-hardware/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[personal]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 12 Oct 2021 13:52:18 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Technology]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=20</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Well, this might seem to be weird, but, yes, I&#8217;m that guy which will test software even of hardware isn&#8217;t officially supported on latest revision. Let me explain situation: I&#8217;m currently running Windows 11 Pro on my recent (somewhat recent) purchase of HP Z240 Tower Workstation. Reasons to buy workstation was simple: my laptop (good [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Well, this might seem to be weird, but, yes, I&#8217;m that guy which will test software even of hardware isn&#8217;t officially supported on latest revision.</p>
<p>Let me explain situation: I&#8217;m currently running Windows 11 Pro on my recent (somewhat recent) purchase of HP Z240 Tower Workstation.<br />
Reasons to buy workstation was simple: my laptop (good old Toshiba C850-1JG) just did&#8217;t wanted to start after regular maintenance, it was motherboard issue, so I went on search to buy realtive cheap desktop which can be upgraded or heck even had some dedicated GPU from brands like HP, Dell or others. Choice to buy this workstation was simple &#8211; pricing for it was super cheap, even cheaper then Intel 4gen based HP&#8217;s with more RAM, SSD already in it and some kind of cheap graphics card like GTX750 Ti or something in that range (price was about 100€, other machines were over that price, but when I saw specs I went, well, ugradeable with more RAM, SSD and maybe some GPU later on, I will buy it).</p>
<p>Now here are specifications of workstation (which was partially upgraded from purchase, spent like 20€ in upgrades, some parts had already in backup from laptop like 480GB SSD which is now 2 and half years old):<br />
CPU: Intel Xeon E3-1225 V5<br />
RAM: 12GB DDR4 (1x4GB 2133MHz + 1x8GB 2400MHz@2133MHz)<br />
GPU: Intel HD Graphics P530<br />
SSD: Crucial BX500 480GB<br />
HDD: Western Digital WD5000AZLX-60K2TA0 500GB<br />
HDD2: Western Digital Green 1TB<br />
Optical: HP HLDS DVD-ROM<br />
PSU: 280W 80+ Gold HP OEM<br />
WiFi Adapter: Tp-Link Archer T2U Nano AC600 USB Adapter<br />
Case: HP Z240 Tower (OEM)</p>
<p>You might get idea, well, this is decent machine, what gives except CPU that you can&#8217;t officially upgrade to Windows 11, even with notification about unsuported CPU &#8211; here is reason: when I bought machine on back it said this: TPM is disabled and product key which I got is for Windows 7 Pro OA China which mandates that TPM can&#8217;t be enabled no matter what. Yup, I got machine from some company which got it, as second hand rig, and person said that they upgraded to new machines and they gave it to them, so I was buyer which paid how much he wanted for a rig.</p>
<p>For that reason I couldn&#8217;t find or even edit UEFI BIOS to enable TPM 1.2 (and upgrade chipset to 2.0 using firmware update when this machine supports it, thanks HP Suport site) and couldn&#8217;t have officially Windows 11 on this rig. Speaking of it, one laptop is officially upgraded to Windows 11 Education, and that is sister&#8217;s one which is running Zen+ based APU (Ryzen 3 3200U to be precise, pretty decent laptop for price which I paid for it 2 years ago, brand new from store).</p>
<p>So, how the freaking (quack) did you upgraded from Windows 10 to Windows 11 you all might said. For that I will say, simple, found this news on <a href="https://www.ghacks.net/2021/09/27/mediacreationtool-bat-download-windows-11-isos-and-bypass-system-compatibility-checks/">Ghacks website</a> and <a href="https://github.com/AveYo/MediaCreationTool.bat">GitHub page</a> of project, used it to create then latest build of Windows 11 with Skip TPM and CPU check batch runned up, mounted created ISO image trough Windows 10, and started auto.bat file which did upgrade process.</p>
<p>It was seamless, it took like 45 minutes from start of upgrade to final desktop. And even kept all of settings of mine, and licences for apps which I would need to deactivate, and later on reactivate if I did fresh install.</p>
<p>Overall, machine is running as seamless as it can for hardware that is inside, no major issues and finaly, it works with official RTM build which is on day of writing this post 22000.194.</p>
<p>Cover image is screenshot which I created for sharing with people who didn&#8217;t believed me that even 3.5 years old workstation hardware don&#8217;t support Windows 11.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/upgrading-from-windows-10-to-windows-11-on-unsupported-hardware/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Short, but useful review of Realme 6s</title>
		<link>/short-but-useful-review-of-realme-6s/</link>
					<comments>/short-but-useful-review-of-realme-6s/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[personal]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 01 Jun 2021 13:49:42 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Reviews]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=18</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[So, this will be short and creative review of Realme 6s which was bought from our mobile operator for super cheap. Specifications of device can be found on GSMArena. There are few changes which aren&#8217;t noted in GSMArena are NFC which works (yeah, it works, tested it with Google Pay and Revolut Visa card and [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>So, this will be short and creative review of Realme 6s which was bought from our mobile operator for super cheap.</p>
<p>Specifications of device can be found <a href="https://www.gsmarena.com/realme_6s-10268.php">on GSMArena</a>. There are few changes which aren&#8217;t noted in GSMArena are NFC which works (yeah, it works, tested it with Google Pay and <a href="https://revolut.com/referral/markobth0!MASO">Revolut</a> Visa card and yes, it works fine).</p>
<p>Just to be clear, this was and still is my secondary device which I mostly use to watch some videos (pirated mostly and YouTube), play games on that smooth 90Hz refresh rate LCD Display and do some thing that I don&#8217;t wanna to do on my main <a href="/month-of-usage-for-xiaomi-redmi-note-9-pro-better-known-as-review-of-phone/">Xiaomi Redmi Note 9 Pro</a> like test out new applications.</p>
<p>As a matter of fact, this device have separate Google Accounts and it is also set up to be used with old Xiaomi Mi Band 4 (and yes, don&#8217;t judge me but I&#8217;m using Mi Band 5 for few months now and I&#8217;m impressed how better detection&#8217;s are, but more about all of it later on or in next post.)</p>
<h2>Device Specifications and nit pickings</h2>
<p>So, yeah. I will note some exceptional specifications like 30W Super Dart/VOOC Charging (yeah, Realme is sub-brand of Oppo) and device charges in like a hour. It is powerful and chargers at 15W while connected through Xiaomi&#8217;s 33W Power brick.</p>
<p>Another nitpicking is that phone is sometimes bit sluggish with 4GB of RAM. That is from guy who use multiple devices and main one is Xiaomi with 6GB is RAM. And yeah, sometimes it looks faster then Xiaomi because of 90Hz LCD.</p>
<h2>Cameras</h2>
<p>Now for part which was tested a lot but lot of photos are private ones. Some examples can be found on <a href="https://photos.app.goo.gl/zsZUYq5SQKToEXn96">Google Photos Gallery</a>. With main 48Mpx camera I can say that shots are fine. I mean, after 8 months of using crazy camera systems from main phone this was a well, bit of letdown.</p>
<p>Front facing camera is just fine, seriously my face looks horribly <img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/13.1.0/72x72/1f602.png" alt="😂" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" />. Examples are in Gallery.</p>
<p>Video examples unfortienatly didn&#8217;t created, or if it were created those are private ones.</p>
<p>On plus side, there is port of <a href="https://forum.xda-developers.com/t/best-gcam7-3-port-for-realme-6-rmx2001.4139319/">GCam</a>, but it is created with config for Realme 6, not 6s (which have different camera systems, more differences about phones can be found <a href="https://www.gsmarena.com/compare.php3?idPhone1=10268&amp;idPhone2=10113">on GSMArena</a>.</p>
<h2>Battery and Conclusion</h2>
<p>As for battery life of this 4300mAh battery, I can say few words &#8211; it can survive my usage. Seriously, even when I put my main SIM Card in phone for a week with 4G, GPS, NFC, WiFi and brightness all way with Auto (as I was mostly outside or in early morning going to Driving School Lessons) it survived day and half mostly. I say mostly, as there was few days when battery did take me one day to melt it down to 10% from 100%. Other days battery can survive 2 or more days with SIM card in it and without 4G enabled but with lot of YouTube shenanigans. This means that battery can get in 6+ hours of Screen on Time, which is perfect.</p>
<p>In conclusion: device is fine, I mean, updates are sort-of regular (as of writing this device is still on Android 10 but with April 2021 patch) and it should be great second device. Or maybe somebody from who device break will get it, who knows what future do for it.</p>
<p>Cover image is shot on Xiaomi Redmi Note 9 Pro, this review was written on old tablet, current desktop and this device. All images and videos are from Realme 6s.</p>
<p>Revolut link is my affiliate link which supports my works.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/short-but-useful-review-of-realme-6s/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Android user experience of using iOS for a month</title>
		<link>/android-user-experience-of-using-ios-for-a-month/</link>
					<comments>/android-user-experience-of-using-ios-for-a-month/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[personal]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 23 Sep 2020 11:37:19 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Reviews]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=16</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Or as another title would be – from broken Android phone to iOS without any other choice. This unwanted migration started while on second day of vacation when I accidentally broke my Samsung Galaxy A7 (2018) which I was using at that time. Phone broke that even service center wouldn’t service it without paying almost [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Or as another title would be – <em>from broken Android phone to iOS without any other choice.</em></p>
<p>This unwanted migration started while on second day of vacation when I accidentally broke my <a href="https://idzan.eu/long-term-review-of-samsung-galaxy-a7-2018/">Samsung Galaxy A7 (2018)</a> which I was using at that time. Phone broke that even service center wouldn’t service it without paying almost 150€ for display replacement. And what was weird coincidence phone broke on Sunday, which really fucked me up for a about 30 hours until I got Apple iPhone 6. Thank God that I used prior to breaking device 4G and Hotspot feature were enabled to get 2 files on friends laptop from his Google Drive which helped me to connect on my laptop and get to search phone for 100€ or less (used devices market was TBH <img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/13.1.0/72x72/1f4a9.png" alt="💩" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /> at that time and near place I was plus almost everybody wanted way more then phones are worth).</p>
<p>I got that <a href="https://www.gsmarena.com/apple_iphone_6-6378.php">iPhone 6</a> with original packaging, unused EarPods, original cable (which I had to replace with some off-brand braided cable as soon as I got home because it was bit broken which annoyed me), some case and screen protector (that 2 items got for free because I said to guy, I can pay you 500 Croatian Kuna for device if you can get it to me and he got to me and gave me new case and new screen protector as gift as I paid what he wanted).</p>
<p>On day that I got device, most of time using it was spent on installing apps and configuring them (at least some basic apps like WhatsApp, Facebook, Instagram and banking applications). Thank God all apps that I use on daily basis were available on App Store.</p>
<p>During initial setup phone was still on iOS 11, but few days later and few gigabytes of mobile network later (because WiFi reception at another location where as family got to stay was really bad on all devices) it was updated to iOS 12.4.8 which is latest available version of iOS for this device.</p>
<p>Let’s talk about experience switching from Android 10 with OneUI 2.0 to iPhone 6 and iOS 12.4.8 – it was sort-of seamless. I mean, I have been using iPhone’s prior to this as work phones but only for brief periods of time (mostly weekends and once for a week while our Galaxy Note 8 got to Service Center). I missed few great features like Dark Mode and Android Back button, but not a big deal.</p>
<p>Now, let’s talk big fish in this sea – connectivity. It is fine for 4G (LTE), but for WiFi and Bluetooth is was horrendous. I mean seriously, with other phones I can get WiFi from my room where is router up to living room which is about 9m away with 2 walls between, but with iPhone I would need to use 4G just to get network in living room. Plus, even if I connected to sister’s AP (created as repeater for his room to have better network coverage) WiFi was horrible.</p>
<p>For a Bluetooth – well I had to be with receiver on (now old) <a href="http://www.s-box.biz/en/artikl/6464">SBox BT218</a> headset in visible positioning to iPhone otherwise it would be song – stop for a second (connection drop) – song for minute – move a bit to left with receiver and losing connection for a few seconds until I gave up and connected EarPods.</p>
<p>Otherwise stability of device was good, specs are perfect for this good old device.</p>
<p>Battery life wasn’t perfect but it was usable with <a href="https://www.mi.com/ph/20000mAh-mi-power-bank-2c/">Power Bank</a> and cable near me at all times as device could survive about 7-8 hours with 1 to 2 hours of SoT with bit of 4G, photo shooting and regular calls. On plus side, still have original battery inside with 70% of Battery Life left in it.</p>
<p>In that week I shot almost 500 photos and got few videos too in 1080p 60FPS (which I enabled as soon as I got device, that was switch in smoothness from 1080p 30FPS that I used on Samsung).</p>
<p>Now, camera is just fine for normal shots in good lightning, I can’t say anything bad about it. But at night and darker situations it is, well, bit of dog <img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/13.1.0/72x72/1f4a9.png" alt="💩" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" />. Seriously, I had to edit photos later just to gain some brightness and ISO so photos can be shared to others from vacation.</p>
<p>Some examples of shots can be found in <a href="https://photos.app.goo.gl/MoRLiB7waq2cTr296">Google Photos Gallery</a><br />
(mix of daily shots and night shots).</p>
<p>Here are some videos in various lightning situations, all shot at 1080p 60FPS.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Ws89E77LBAs&amp;list=PL3kVxMe9MNP2QeMMGmHx0tbZw8w3Zt_nZ">View video examples on YouTube Playlist</a></p>
<p>Now here is conclusion in two parts – how it was to get back on Android and in part two I will say for what is now this device used.</p>
<p>Main conclusion is – this device served me well until I got <a href="https://idzan.eu/month-of-usage-for-xiaomi-redmi-note-9-pro-better-known-as-review-of-phone/">Xiaomi Redmi Note 9 Pro</a>. Device despite age of it is still capable to be working phone for somebody who is careful with battery or replaced it. After switching back to Android I don’t miss any feature from iPhone to be honest.</p>
<p>And now, for what is now used after switching to Android phone back – it is used as music player and YouTube player prior sleeping. Yup, because of size it is perfect for those things at night.</p>
<p>Cover image is shot on Xiaomi Redmi Note 9 Pro, this review was written on iPhone 6 and all other photos and videos are from iPhone 6 and are my work.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/android-user-experience-of-using-ios-for-a-month/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Month of usage for Xiaomi Redmi Note 9 Pro (better known as Review of phone)</title>
		<link>/month-of-usage-for-xiaomi-redmi-note-9-pro-better-known-as-review-of-phone/</link>
					<comments>/month-of-usage-for-xiaomi-redmi-note-9-pro-better-known-as-review-of-phone/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[personal]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 17 Sep 2020 11:34:49 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Reviews]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=14</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[So, let’s premise this review with one important thing – I’m writing this review from this phone which I’m reviewing. Yes, I love it so much that I wrote it in Notes application and later on copied in Google Docs so it can be synced with PC from which it is published. What a perfect [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>So, let’s premise this review with one important thing – I’m writing this review from this phone which I’m reviewing. Yes, I love it so much that I wrote it in Notes application and later on copied in Google Docs so it can be synced with PC from which it is published. What a perfect combination for writing review for Xiaomi Redmi Note 9 Pro.</p>
<p>Now, why I bought this device and how it is to use it. Reason that I bought it for around 210€ (approximation of price from Croatian Kuna) in August of this year is that I had to move back to Android after a month with iOS (to be precise iPhone 6 running iOS 12.4.5). Plus I moved to iOS just because that was only option to buy when my <a href="https://idzan.eu/long-term-review-of-samsung-galaxy-a7-2018/">Samsung Galaxy A7 (2018)</a> got broken while on vacation on Krapanj Island.</p>
<p>Here is a thing – I wanted to move from Samsung to Xiaomi right about this time because pricing of solid mid-range Samsung phones went nuts. But really nuts. For example on day when I bought my phone cheapest and really next stepping stone with solid phone was Samsung Galaxy A51 which was priced about 350€ (approximation from Croatian Kuna).</p>
<h3>Battery and Specifications of Xiaomi Redmi Note 9 Pro</h3>
<p>For my budget (which was around 300€ at that time) this is perfect device. For starters, with specifications it is great for higher end of mid-range devices. For me it is higher end because it is having Gorilla Glass 5 on front and back and because of Camera Specifications. Basics for Xiaomi Redmi Note 9 Pro are Snapdragon Qualcomm 720G which is based on 8nm process, 6GB of RAM, 64 or 128GB of storage which is expandable via microSD cards, 64MP + 8MP + 5MP +2MP Cameras on back with 16MP Camera in punch-hole design on 6.67 inch 2400 by 1080px LCD. More details about specifications can be found on <a href="https://www.gsmarena.com/xiaomi_redmi_note_9_pro-10217.php">GSMArena</a>. As you might see, this is Global version of phone, just to note because there is same name for this phone for Indian market (and Indian model is for other parts of world known as <a href="https://www.gsmarena.com/xiaomi_redmi_note_9s-10147.php">Xiaomi Redmi Note 9S</a>.</p>
<p>Some things that got me to this phone and not <a href="https://www.gsmarena.com/xiaomi_mi_note_10_lite-10183.php">Xiaomi Mi Note 10 Lite</a> which I could get in my budget are fingerprint reader in power button and expandable storage via microSD card.</p>
<p>Now to review – Xiaomi Redmi Note 9 Pro is great device as you might not see until now. As I’m mostly mid to heavy duty user it can keep it up with my usage.</p>
<p>In start I have to note big battery – 5020mAh. This is major improvement in my phone collection. The biggest battery with Turbo Charging. Yes, charging. In box we got 33W Power Brick with USB-PD and Quick Charge Compatibility. This brick with original USB-C to USB-A cable can charge device in about hour. Seriously, once I got around 18% of battery charge in morning and I had to go to daily biking and after about hour it got charged to 100%.</p>
<p>As I’m talking about battery and charging – this brick of battery can survive in average for 2 and half days with full charge on my even heavier usage with average of 7+ hours of Screen on Time (SoT). My usage is WiFi, 4G (only when I’m not near WiFi), Bluetooth (for connection to Xiaomi Mi Band 4, Xiaomi Mi True Wireless Earbuds Basic S and computer when near it), GPS (for sports tracking in Mi Fit and Google Fit) and finally NFC (as most of payments trough COVID-19 is with NFC and Google Pay connected to multiple cards).</p>
<p>As for other specifications, well I have nothing special to say. I’m experienced with mid-range specifications of phones, this Xiaomi Redmi Note 9 Pro is snappy in day to day usage. Even for lighter gaming (tried with Call of Duty Mobile for few hours) it is all fine. Screen brightness isn’t like Sasmung Galaxy A7 (2018) which was rocking AMOLED display, but is readable even on bright sunny day.</p>
<h3>Camera tests and shots from Xiaomi Redmi Note 9 Pro</h3>
<p>Now to major part of this phone and why I got it – cameras. Yes, I use phone cameras for almost all of my photos which are published online and which will be seen in Photography and Graphics Portfolio (when I finish design for it). Main camera is 64MP with f1.9 which is bit “worse” then previous camera on Samsung phone, but for me it isn’t big change. Camera shots from main camera sensor and make it 16MP in final form just to make file size smaller. And sensor is really great.</p>
<p>There is also 64MP mode which create <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=6YDoowoYzOI">big chungus</a> of photos. Those are really big so I will provide to see them <a href="https://photos.app.goo.gl/Zg1uYFcm3gTK1VLf7">Google Photos</a> Gallery.</p>
<p>For night mode which is available in Camera application photos are solid. Most of them are shot from hand without any stand or tripod. Also for this phone is available Google Camera (GCam) mod which enables Astrophotography Mode. Those Astrophotography Mode shots are looking like it is mostly daylight and not freaking night.</p>
<p>Ultra-wide camera can create pretty much great shots just like old Samsung phone.</p>
<p>Macro camera is also fine, it can keep it up with details on nearby objects.</p>
<p>As for selfie camera, well I can say that is perfect in my honest opinion (as I can say myself <img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/13.1.0/72x72/1f923.png" alt="🤣" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" />).</p>
<p>All shots can be viewed in <a href="https://photos.app.goo.gl/uUhjembAFvYJU8hq8">Google Photos Gallery</a> with all details as I backup all images at Original Quality.</p>
<p>Video quality is solid for a phone with this price. I can say that videos are better then on old device. In 4K recording mode it doesn’t have EIS, but in 1080p modes (30 and 60FPS are here) it is having EIS. There is no OIS, but EIS is just fine. Down below are few examples of 4K 30FPS, 1080p 60FPS and 1080p 30 FPS Shots created in this month of using it.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=DquFrR1G258&amp;list=PLjZBK267PpJFMgFR-ZnDgKO74ckpYtlAf">View video examples in this YouTube Playlist</a></p>
<p>In conclusion of this brief review of phone which I’m using for a month now I can say few things and those are – man, I freaking love Xiaomi eco-system. Especially for somebody who prior to buying this phone had Xiaomi Powerbank 2C in 20000mAh Capacity and Xiaomi Mi Band 4 (prior to buying it I had some cheap clone of it which broke in less then a month of usage and battery was <img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/13.1.0/72x72/1f4a9.png" alt="💩" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" />). With this I will keep it up with Xiaomi devices in future which might get to me Xiaomi flagship phones in Mi Series, not like today in Redmi mid-range based phones. As big plus, I’m currently moving whole family to Xiaomi phones from their Samsung’s and Cubot’s.</p>
<p>All photos and videos are my property, and all (except cover image which is shot with iPhone 6) are created with Xiaomi Redmi Note 9 Pro within this month of usage. All images are hosted on Imgur and Google Photos as they are too much for this server.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/month-of-usage-for-xiaomi-redmi-note-9-pro-better-known-as-review-of-phone/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Long-Term Review of Samsung Galaxy A7 (2018)</title>
		<link>/long-term-review-of-samsung-galaxy-a7-2018/</link>
					<comments>/long-term-review-of-samsung-galaxy-a7-2018/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[personal]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 14 Mar 2020 12:33:02 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Reviews]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=12</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[So, in short for people who don’t want to read this post – phone is perfect mid-range device, cameras are great in daily shooting situations and in night based times shots are fine. Battery can support it for 2 days with mid to heavy usage patterns. Plus it is pretty much supported device which will [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>So, in short for people who don’t want to read this post – phone is perfect mid-range device, cameras are great in daily shooting situations and in night based times shots are fine. Battery can support it for 2 days with mid to heavy usage patterns. Plus it is pretty much supported device which will get Android 10 with One UI 2.0.</p>
<p>OK, after TL;DR section let’s go to why I chose this device and how it is to use it for a almost a year with various patterns of usage. I used it pretty much heavy in start, lowered usage while on vacation and lately it is on mid usage.</p>
<p>Why I chose this device is one question – I decided to get it because our ISP and Mobile Operator here in Croatia in store where we went didn’t had Samsung Galaxy A50 or Nokia 6.1 Plus in Stock when we decided to move from another ISP to them. That was a bit, well, weird but yet – it was smaller store and that was fine for me. We head to buy 2 devices because we moved 2 phone numbers from another Mobile Operator to this one.</p>
<p>After few days of super heavy usage which included WiFi, Mobile Data, Dark Mode and Bluetooth on all time I saw that phone can survive for almost 2 full work days. That was nice. Later on while in lower time of usage phone survived for almost 3.5 days and then I disabled Bluetooth which I now use only when I want to connect to my Bluetooth Headset (Not so popular brand but it was cheap as f***). Nice one for 3300mAh Battery.</p>
<p>For specs of device I will provide it from <a href="https://www.gsmarena.com/samsung_galaxy_a7_(2018)-9340.php">GSMArena</a> because device have various combinations of RAM and Storage. Our devices are 4GB RAM and 64GB of Storage version.</p>
<p>Screen is perfect size for my hands. It is perfect size, but well, I tried lately before this “human malware” some newer Samsung Devices from Operators Big Store and those are too big for my hands (note: those devices were Samsung Galaxy S20, Samsung Galaxy S20 Ultra, Samsung Galaxy Z Flip and Samsung Galaxy Fold).</p>
<p>Software is perfect, well, for me it is way better then Stock Android with some features like included Screen Recorder, scrolling Screenshot, double security with Knox etc. It is pretty much almost latest version of Android. Now it is on Android 9.0 with Samsung’s OneUI 1.0 with Security Patch for February of 2020. Yup, this device is pretty much up-to-date with Security Patches and with features which are perfect for daily usage I can’t explain anything else. Except that this device will get Android 10 with OneUI 2.0 later in 2020. ( April 2020. is time to get released in Europe), after old flagships get it. That would be great for user who used phones with max 2 update cycles and only got one (khm Huawei and Samsung in old days).</p>
<p>Now, it is big time – Cameras time. How are they in my usage?</p>
<p>Answer to question above is – perfect. I mean, really perfect. Only thing missing for me it is granular Pro Mode which had only Huawei P9 Lite (2016) but otherwise camera is great. Some shots are below in this gallery where all photos are uncompressed. For detailed informations about Photos check them out on updated <a href="https://photos.app.goo.gl/DWLUvaWKBCaYEYYG8">Gallery via Google Photos</a>.</p>
<p>As for video Quality I will refer to couple of videos linked below. All are in various forms which camera supports like Regular Mode, Time lapse mode and finally in Wide Angle camera mode.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=-eSHo6w_TT8&amp;list=PL3kVxMe9MNP2isfPtt747ZklZX2yvZFAa">View video examples on YouTube</a></p>
<p>As a conclusion I will say that this device is perfect for me, it will survive one more year of my usage and finally – it will be replaced with another mid-range device next year from A Series or maybe older flagship (hint: Galaxy S20).</p>
<p>Photos and videos in this review are my property.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/long-term-review-of-samsung-galaxy-a7-2018/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Moving away from Adobe</title>
		<link>/moving-away-from-adobe/</link>
					<comments>/moving-away-from-adobe/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[personal]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 05 Mar 2020 12:31:56 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Technology]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=10</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Soo, it took me a while but I’m now finally (yes, finally) Adobe CC Free. What does it mean to us, except that you wouldn’t use Adobe CC Apps anymore and would use other tools. Well, this might be interesting to you all who have problems with Adobe Creative Cloud which is expensive and it [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Soo, it took me a while but I’m now finally (yes, finally) Adobe CC Free.</p>
<p>What does it mean to us, except that you wouldn’t use Adobe CC Apps anymore and would use other tools. Well, this might be interesting to you all who have problems with Adobe Creative Cloud which is expensive and it is crashy at moments, especially in last two iterations.</p>
<p>What is gives up, why moving from Adobe – well, for me it is big move because I can’t buy Adobe CC here in Croatia without annual payment of almost 1000€ without paying for a month-to-month as I would like. Until now I mostly well <em>pirated</em> Adobe apps, and even when I found some <em>cheap</em> and <em>seems legit</em> variants I paid (yup, paid) for them to find that those versions are shared accounts or accounts with hacked passwords which is problematic when user logs you out and you need to login again and remove computers which you think that is not in use.</p>
<p>So, to which apps I moved – here is list of apps that I tried and on which I started to use after Adobe apps.</p>
<p><strong>Adobe Photoshop</strong> – for this app there is lot of alternatives, but I have switched to <strong>Affinity Photo</strong>. Yup, Serif’s Affinity Photo. Why – just because in version 1.8 it supports Smart Objects from Photoshop. This keeped me away from moving on Photoshop, but now when it is available in Affinity Photo I said finally – <em>Good bye, Auf wiedersehen</em> Photoshop, welcome Affinity. As backup apps I’m running <strong>GIMP</strong> and <strong>Paint.net</strong> just because I know how to use them and they are my favorites for it. Just to know it – I purchased Affinity tools view edit and note below.</p>
<p><strong>Adobe Illustrator</strong> – and for this there is few apps which I use and main is <strong>Affinity Designer</strong> and <strong>Inkscape</strong>. Both are great, but Inkscape is free and open-source which helps me when I’m on my Linux machine. Both apps are great and both are functional for my usage of them which is mostly for small logo creation or for edits on SVG files.</p>
<p><strong>Adobe Premiere Pro</strong> – for this app I have already alternative in Sony (now Magix) <strong>Vegas Pro 13</strong> which I bought (yup, bought) while back on Steam when it was on big sale. I always preferred Sony Vegas because it was easier to learn how-to edit in it. Before buying Vegas Pro I bought <strong>Movie Studio 13 Platinum</strong> just because I wanted to get into legit usage of Sony tools in old company. Plus, on this Winter Sale on Steam I also bought <strong>Movavi Video Studio</strong> which helped me to create simple edits with cool transitions for project which never saw lights on YouTube but it was shown on one presentation. For my Linux rig I use <strong>Kdenlive</strong> which is good alternative even to Sony Vegas Pro.</p>
<p><strong>Adobe After Effects</strong> – and this is weird app which I used once or twice mostly, and for all things after that I never touched it, but if I would ever need it I will use <em>DaVinci Resolve</em> with Fusion. For now, for small VFX I can use Sony Vegas Pro.</p>
<p><strong>Adobe Acrobat and Acrobat Reader</strong> – this is my old toolkit which is replaced with couple of online apps for merging PDF files and I use native exports from apps to PDF. Simple as it is. And for Reader, well, <strong>SumatraPDF</strong> is great and also new browsers have good PDF readers.</p>
<p><strong>Adobe Dreamweaver</strong> – who the duck use it, really?!? I have switched from it to Code Editors like <em>Notepad++, VS Code and Sublime Text</em> (bought it when I worked in previous company) and for WYSIWYG editors there a lot of alternatives like <em>Wix, Weebly, SquareSpace</em> and for WordPress there are good editors like <em>Elementor</em> and <em>WPBakery</em>.</p>
<p><strong>Adobe XD</strong> – oh boy. I used it few times and found better alternatives in <strong>Figma</strong> (which is best app for all Operating Systems because it is web based), <strong>Gravit Designer</strong> and <strong>Lunacy</strong> (which can load Sketch files).</p>
<p>This is just my personal apps which I started using after Adobe Creative Cloud for as long as I know for it and previously as Creative Studio for years. It is now basically relearning new shortcuts for Affinity apps and learning new stuff about apps like Figma which I started using lately.</p>
<p>Otherwise, this was long journey which started in September of 2019. and it is finished now with release of 1.8 for Affinity “Suite”.</p>
<p><em>Note:</em> You can purchase license for bargain price on eBay from seller <a href="https://www.ebay.com/usr/kingsoft2020">kingsoft2020</a> – he is fast with delivery and he will respond to your answer fast.</p>
<p>Cover Photo is personal screenshot of programs in &#8220;usage&#8221;.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/moving-away-from-adobe/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Using Huawei P9 Lite for a year</title>
		<link>/using-huawei-p9-lite-for-a-year/</link>
					<comments>/using-huawei-p9-lite-for-a-year/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[personal]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 27 May 2018 11:30:25 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Reviews]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=7</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Or as I would write this alternative title: Long term review of Huawei P9 Lite with 3GB of RAM. So, here it is. A review of my daily smartphone after almost one year of using it. In that year I had used other phones trough work devices like Samsung Galaxy S8, Samsung Galaxy A5 (2017) [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Or as I would write this alternative title: <em>Long term review of Huawei P9 Lite with 3GB of RAM</em>.</p>
<p>So, here it is. A review of my daily smartphone after almost one year of using it. In that year I had used other phones trough work devices like Samsung Galaxy S8, Samsung Galaxy A5 (2017) and even Samsung Galaxy Note 8. Also I got it to service center once (more on that later) and got new one (again more later). Today is right one year and one month of using phone so it is perfect timing for a long term review.</p>
<p>To start I have to write some specs, but I actually don’t need because of fantastic web site named <a href="https://www.gsmarena.com/">GSMArena.com</a> where you can find <a href="https://www.gsmarena.com/huawei_p9_lite-7983.php#vns-l31">specifications of this phone</a>. But for some important notes I had to say that my device is Dual SIM version with 3GB of RAM, better known with Model number VNS-L31.</p>
<p>Here it is in daily usage – it is snappy as it can be. <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Huawei_EMUI">EMUI</a> 5.0.1 on based Android 7.0 Nougat is good with this hardware. I didn’t got any major hiccups or problems in this year of using this phone. OK, I had some minor hiccups and random reboots from time to time, mostly when I don’t reboot phone for more then a month or after updates. Yes, this phone still receives updates most of updates are Security Patches by Google for Android. Latest update got us May 1st 2018 Security Patch with some Huawei specific updates to their software.</p>
<p>Now, let’s get to some important stuff – how battery survived a year. For my usage I can say superb. It can still get 2 days of moderate usage with about 4 hours of Screen on Time (SoT) with all important stuff turned on like WiFi, Mobile Data, GPS and lately Bluetooth. Bluetooth connection is used for connecting my lovely smartwatch and Wireless Headphones (Started switching more and more to them for music listening while running). If I don’t use any connection what so ever (which happens from time to time) it can survive up to 4 days. Keep in mind that happens rarely but I can tell that battery can survive weekend without charging it.</p>
<p>To the screen, and well, what to say about it. It is OK, not super bright and not so dim as I would like it (looking at you Samsung Galaxy Note 8 just in front of me).</p>
<p>Camera, oh boy camera is beautiful. Even tough it doesn’t have all bells and whistles of larger and hardware better Huawei P9 like Leica branded Camera lenses it can make pretty much good shots. With solidly implemented HDR and Professional (Manual) Mode it can make some good looking scenes even better. For instance, here is shot made without Manual Mode tweaks:</p>
<p><a href="https://flic.kr/p/Ks7axd">Open image on Flickr</a></p>
<p>And here it is with Manual Mode:</p>
<p><a href="https://flic.kr/p/Ks7aVN">Open image on Flickr</a></p>
<p>As you all might see in distance, sky is blue which is better shown in image below with Manual Mode. Also clouds aren’t so grey they are as shown in second image. This can happen when you actually have time to make tweaks. For quick shots this phone is good.</p>
<p>For videos I can say that 1080p with EIS is great, even for night based shots with only one lamp turned on as you can see in next video, <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=i9FT6WJ7WIo">which can be viewed on YouTube</a>.</p>
<p>Physical hardware of device can survive drops and falls from few heights. It have some minor scratches and some screen issues (like dead pixels, but actually it happened while phone got dropped to floor with Tempered Glass Screen protector from height of about 1.5 meters. Touch is working fine, but screen now have some bleed under display).</p>
<p>Now to some bad things that can happen so device get to Service Center. First problem was with some update in early Android 6.0 Marshmallow to Android 7.0 Nougat days. After update phone got to service center because of boot loop which I couldn’t fix. Another time when phone got to service center, well then I made problem. Actually I hard bricked device with testing unlocking boot loader and installing latest update. With that problem I got one good guy in Service Center which fixed phone to me with “refurbishing” it (he actually got me new phone with Warranty help, I’m still thanking him for getting me a new device).</p>
<p>Overall, device is great mid range based device with almost latest Android OS. If I was better thinking almost year ago I would go to [Samsung Galaxy A5 (2017)](<a href="https://www.gsmarena.com/samsung_galaxy_a5_(2017)-8494.php">https://www.gsmarena.com/samsung_galaxy_a5_(2017)-8494.php</a>, but still after Doogee phone it was improvement. For my next phone I think keeping up with Huawei, but after some <a href="https://www.androidpolice.com/2018/05/24/huawei-halts-bootloader-unlock-program-indefinitely/">not so good news for Developers Community</a> I think that my next phone is some Samsung device or maybe Nokia phone, but until then I can wait.</p>
<p>Photos and videos in this review are my property.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/using-huawei-p9-lite-for-a-year/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
